Guide to the Willard B. Golovin Papers, 1882-1974 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Willard B. Golovin papers 1882-1974 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Golovin, Willard B.
15.0 linear feet Extent: 10,500 Items
Artist, advertising executive (Willard B. Golovin Co.) and director of an art gallery (Bayer Gallery) in New York, N.Y. Collection spans the years 1882-1974 and includes correspondence, tear sheets, clippings, printed material and original artwork that document Golovin's careers running the Willard B. Golovin agency and the Bayer Gallery. Clients include Aberle, Frances Denney, Glen Guard clothiers, and Harry Winston jewelers. There are also files relating to support efforts during World War II and a series of posters addressing absenteeism in war work industries. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.Cataloged from inventory.
RL.00463
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Willard B. Golovin Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012.
Collection Overview
Collection spans the years 1882-1974 and includes correspondence, tear sheets, clippings, printed material and original artwork that document Golovin's careers running the Willard B. Golovin agency and the Bayer Gallery. Clients include Aberle, Frances Denney, Glen Guard clothiers, and Harry Winston jewelers. There are also files relating to support efforts during World War II and a series of posters addressing absenteeism in war work industries.
Collection Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Personal and General Files; Agency Files; Financial Records; Advertisements; and Large-Format Materials. Where possible or practical, original folder titles were maintained.
Subject Headings
Golovin, Willard B. (Willard Bayer), 1908-2001; Advertising; Advertising -- History; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- History; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Art museums; Art museums -- Collection management; Art museums -- New York (State); Art museums -- United States; Art museum directors; War posters; War posters, American; War posters, American -- 1940-1950; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- United States; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives
Howard Scott Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company Account Files
J. Walter Thompson Company World War II Advertising Collection
OAAA Archives
War Effort Mobilization Campaigns Poster Collection
Detailed Description of Collection
- Personal and General, 1929-1973 and undated
  - Bayer Art Gallery
    - American Painters/ United Cerebral Palsy, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Art (international)/Art News/Job applications, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Assorted images, gallery collection, undated (Box 1)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 1)
    - Curteis, William, 1957-1959, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Envelope of tickets to exhibitions, Sunken Meadow Gallery of Contemporary Art, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Henri Matisse drawings, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Knize, Inc./Oskar Kokoschka exhibit, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1959-1973 (Box 1)
    - Operations record, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Serena Rotastein exhibit, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Aberle Ballet, letters, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
    - Aberle correspondence binder, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, old, 1935-1949, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Current correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 2)
    - Inventory, letters, 1937-1942 (Box 2)
    - Letters, 1935-1950, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Letters, Aberle, other, 1941-1953 (Box 2)
    - Storage, letters, 1942-1953 (Box 2)
    - Trip to Europe, 1949-1951 (Box 3)
  - General
    - Art Directors Club, 1949 (Box 3)
    - Elizabeth Arden, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Expansionists, 1950-1951, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Golovin's travels, 1952 (Box 3)
    - National effort (World War II), 1941-1942, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - NYU seminar, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
    - Photography, 1949-1953 (Box 4)
    - Public praise, 1944-1951 (Box 4)
    - Swiss posters, 1950-1952, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Tax returns, 1946-1964 (Box 4)
    - TV Speech AAAA Eastern Conference, 1950-1954 (Box 4)
  - Peck and Peck
    - Finances, notes, assorted documents, 1930-1933, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Notes, instructions, assorted documents, 1929-1933 (Box 5)
- Agency Files, 1932-1954 and undated
  - Agency management
    - Agency personnel, 1936-1947 (Box 5)
    - Agency ideas/General ideas, 1946-1953 (Box 5)
    - American Newspaper Publishers, 1952 (Box 5)
    - Copyright forms, 1950-1952 (Box 5)
    - Irwing, Berlin Inc., 1946-1948 (Box 5)
    - Operation ideas and old procedures, 1943-1952 (Box 5)
    - Prospects (Box 6)
    - Burlington Mills, 1952 (Box 6)
    - James Grimm 1951-1953 (Box 6)
    - J. P. Stevens1950-1951 (Box 6)
    - Questionaires, prospective advertisers, 1951-1953 (Box 6)
    - Richter's Jewelers Inc., 1952 (Box 6)
  - Agency promotion
    - Agency recognition, 1941-1954 (Box 6)
    - Awards and applications, 1941-1949 (Box 6)
    - Copy, letters for promotion, 1946-1950 (Box 6)
    - Job samples, 1946-1951 (Box 6)
    - Press clippings, 1947-1950 (Box 6)
    - Promotional letters, 1950 (Box 6)
    - Promotions, 1943-1949 (Box 6)
    - Publicity, 1941-1949, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Story of Clix, 1949-1951 (Box 7)
    - Story of WBG Corp., 1932-1953 (Box 7)
    - Tear Sheets, 1951 (Box 7)
  - Campaign ideas
    - Art, 1949 (Box 7)
    - Attitudes of public to advertising, 1951 (Box 7)
    - Copy ideas, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1944-1947 (Box 7)
    - Music promotion, undated (Box 7)
    - Selling ideas, 1946-1949 (Box 7)
    - Why advertise?, undated (Box 7)
  - Frances Denney
    - Authorizations, 1953-1954 (Box 7)
    - Call reports, 1953-1954 (Box 7)
    - Contracts, 1952-1954, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1954, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Cost sheets, 1953-1954 (Box 8)
    - Job samples and proofs, 1953-1954 (Box 8)
    - Meeting reports, 1953-1954, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Production orders, 1953-1954 (Box 9)
    - Schedules, 1953-1954 (Box 9)
    - Starch Report, 1953 (Box 9)
    - Time sheets, 1953-1954 (Box 9)
- Financial Records, 1946-1957 and undated
  - Accounts payable 1946-1952 (Box 9)
  - Bills to clients 1953-1954 (Box 10)
  - Agency financial statements
    - Financial statements, 1950-1954 (Box 10)
    - Production order books, undated (Box 10)
  - Various ledgers
    - Accounts receivable, 1946-1951 (Box 11)
    - Journals, 1951 (Box 11)
    - Willard B. Golovin Company bound ledgers (5 volumes)1947-1950 (Box 11)
  - Willard B. Golovin Company bound ledgers
    - Purchase book (2 volumes), 1946-1951 (Box 12)
    - Receipts/Disbursements, 1946-1947 (Box 12)
    - Receipts/Disbursements (2 volumes), 1948-1951 (Box 13)
  - Willard B. Golovin Company financial books
    - Accounts receivable/Payable, 1946-1954 (Box 14)
    - Mutual payroll book, 1949-1950 (Box 14)
    - Stock certificates, 1946 (Box 14)
    - Willard B. Golovin Company general ledgers, 1951-1952 (Box 15)
  - Willard B. Golovin Company ledgers
    - Employee hours (2 volumes), 1948-1953 (Box 15)
    - Letter from Lucette, 1950-1951 (Box 15)
    - Petty cash, 1946-1948 (Box 15)
    - WBG Sterling Bank, 1953-1957, (1 of 3 folders) (Box 15)
    - WBG Sterling Bank, 1953-1957, (2-3 of 2 folders) (Box 16)
- Advertisements, 1938-1951 and undated
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1947-1951, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Aberle, Inc., 1940-1943 and undated (Box 17)
  - Ameritex, undated (Box 17)
  - AMSCO, undated (Box 17)
  - Anne Miller, 1939 (Box 17)
  - Aralac, undated (Box 17)
  - Bonwit Teller, undated (Box 17)
  - Custombilt pipes, undated (Box 17)
  - Customcraft shoes, undated (Box 17)
  - Eaton's Papers/Henry R. Leeds, 1943 (Box 17)
  - Glen Guard: Individualized clothes, 1944-1945 and undated (Box 18)
  - Greenhill & Daniel/Nautical Togs, circa 1938 (Box 18)
  - Harry Winston Inc. jeweler, 1945-1947 and undated (Box 18)
  - Herald Knitwear/Huddleson, 1952 and undated (Box 18)
  - I & R Morley sportswear, undated (Box 18)
  - Jane Irwill sweaters, 1949 (Box 18)
  - Kaufmann's, Diamond Jubilee, 1946 (Box 18)
  - Lehigh and Lackawanna Warehouse and Transportation, undated (Box 18)
  - Letter from Lucette, 1951 (Box 18)
  - Mallinson Fabrics, American Indian Collection, undated (Box 18)
  - Manchester/Leeds Fabrics, undated (Box 19)
  - Nina cosmetics, undated (Box 19)
  - P.P. Kellogg, stationers, undated, (2 folders) (Box 19)
  - Salomon Furs, undated (Box 19)
  - Schoenfeld & Wolf/Park Lane handbags, undated (Box 19)
  - Slimtite lingerie, undated (Box 19)
  - Starlight Fashions, undated (Box 19)
  - Whitley Tailleurs, undated (Box 19)
  - World War II Absentee posters (Box 20)
    - No.1: They had but one life to give! You have every day (Box 20)
    - No.3: Inaccurate typing may mean mistakes at the front (Box 20)
    - No.4: You can't beat A. Hitler in here (bathroom) (Box 20)
    - No.6: Every minute you are late holds back our fate--Hitler and Hirohito (Box 20)
    - No.7: Your absence has his blessing--Keep in good health to keep on the job (Hitler as angel) (Box 20)
    - No.8: Let your conscience be your guide--Stay on the job--Help America win (Box 20)
    - No.9: Absence makes Hitler's heart grow fonder--keep in good health to keep on the job (Box 20)
    - No.10: There's a mistake somewhere--Concentrate on your job--Errors are serious (Box 20)
    - No.11: Your typewriter may produce the margin for victory--Stay on the job--Every hour every day! (Box 20)
    - No.12: Don't daydream--Your work is vital to victory (Box 20)
    - No.13: Make them happy (Hitler and Hirohito)--Takes lots of time out (Box 20)
    - No.15: You can't beat the Axis in here! (break room)--Stay on the job--Every hour every day! (Box 20)
- Large-Format Materials, 1882-1974 and undated
  - Bayer Gallery clippings, 1959-1974 (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1942-1953 (Box 21)
  - Georgian Press Type Specimen Book, undated (Box 21)
  - Passarelli, book of correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 21)
  - Print Advertisements
    - Ameritex, 1938 (Box 21)
    - Braemer, undated (Box 21)
    - Fisba Fabrics, undated (Box 21)
    - Frances Denney, 1953-1954 and undated (Box 21)
    - Glen Guard clothes, undated (Box 21)
    - Harry Winston, 1945 and undated (Box 21)
    - Peerless robes and sportswear, 1938 (Box 21)
    - Peter Pan fabrics/Henry Glass, undated (Box 21)
    - Slimtite/Weston Underwear, undated (Box 21)
  - Agency promotion ideas and sketches, undated (Box 22)
  - Clippings--Advertising Age, 1949 July 18 (Box 22)
  - Printed material: Chopin, Scherzo and Impromptu score, 1882 (Box 22)
  - Print Advertisements
    - Charles Armour, Prophetics fashion line, undated (Box 22)
    - Frances Denney, undated (Box 22)
    - Frances Denney job book, 1953-1954 (Box 22)
    - Frank Associates, California fabrics, undated (Box 22)
    - Glen Guard clothes, undated (Box 22)
    - Harry Winston, undated (Box 22)
    - Hope Reed/Marshall Fields, 1950 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous (Ameritex, Bonnie Castin rainwear, Herbert R. Leeds, Mallison), 1936 and undated (Box 22)
  - Advertising designs
    - Aberle, Inc., undated (Box 23)
    - Charles Armour, Prophetics fashion line, undated (Box 23)
    - Glen Guard (ggg) clothes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Tewi, undated, (3 folders) (Box 23)
  - Unsorted artwork and advertising designs, undated (Box 24-29)